Let's see if we can push the boundaries a little bit more and make a almost an artificial intelligence
program.
It's not going to be quite AI, but let's say we wanted to try and give some advice.
So this is going to be your personal advisor on what to do in the various seasons.
So let's say pick the the different seasons.
And so we're going to print advice depending on what season it is.
And for each season we're going to print a different piece of advice.
So let's say it's winter.
So winter our advice in winter is that you should dress warmly.
So don't forget to dress warmly if it is winter.
This is really great advice and it's something you should never forget.
Um, right.
So that's our winter advice.
Uh, let's take, uh, the other extreme.
Maybe it's summer.
So our summer advice is don't forget the sunscreen.
You want to go out there and have lots of fun, but, you know, want to put some sunscreen on if it's
going to be too much time in the sun.
Well, how about springtime advice?
So I think springtime.
Beautiful time for taking photos.
So remember your camera.
You've always got your phone on you.
You probably don't even remember your camera.
But anyway, remember your camera so you can get some good pics of the beautiful flowers that are all
springing all over the place.
And then we have autumn, that beautiful season when all the leaves are falling.
So the important thing to remember in autumn is don't forget to jump on the leaves and you must do that.
Everyone's got to go and do that.
Find a big pile of leaves and jump up and down.
So this is our incredible advice that we want to give people based on the season.
Now, obviously if we just run the program like that, that's pretty useless.
I mean, this is going to print four pieces of advice and, you know, that's not particularly useful.
So what we want to do is we need to have a variable that we are going to capture whatever the season
is.
So let's create a variable up at the top and capture whatever the season is.
So this is my season and we can set it to whatever.
So let's say the first one is summer.
So we now need to do something where it's going to check based on what is stored in my season.
It's going to only print one of these for now.
We looked in the previous lesson there's an if else.
Now it can't just check the first one and say is it summer?
And if it isn't, then go and print the next thing it actually needs to check essentially four times.
And this is where we want to introduce you to the next statement, which is the else if statement or
conditional statements have to begin with the if statement.
You can't start with an else statement.
You can't start with the else if statement, which I'm about to show you.
Now they all have to start with the if.
Let's first check if our season variable is equal to summer.
So if my season and remember it's a double equal to is equal to sigma.
Then we want to do something.
Firstly, I'm sure you've realized is I'm not using integers here.
I'm actually using strings.
So with FNL statements you can compare, like I said earlier, a whole lot of different data types.
So here what it's going to do is it's going to check if this variable, which we have set to summer,
is exactly the same as this word here, then it is going to be true.
So if I just changed one letter in here I'll show you later.
It's no longer going to be equal to this.
So if this here, this variable here is exactly the same as this one here, then it's going to be true.
So now we want to print.
This statement to remind people to not forget the sunscreen.
Remember it has to be indented otherwise it won't print it.
So if that is true, it's going to execute the indented statements.
Then now we are going to look at Elsif.
So elsif shortened to just being Lf, which is the way you write it basically means else if this statement
is not true then let's do the next one.
So the next thing we would like to check is if Mathiesen is equal to winter.
Winter.
And if it's winter, we want it to print this dress warmly.
Okay.
Now we have four statements that we want to use, or four reminders that we want to print based on the
season.
So we actually need another elsif now.
So else if my season.
Is equal to spring.
Then we wanted to print.
Remember your camera.
And then lastly, we wanted to print this one for autumn.
Okay.
So I could actually write another elsif statement and put this in here.
But every if statement.
Well, but every else if statement does have to end with an else.
So I could do this in two ways.
Firstly, I could just put in another elsif like my others and check else if my season is equal to autumn.
Then print this over here.
But now we still have to add that else no matter what, because we are doing ourselves.
And then what do we put in here?
I mean, we could write a message, or maybe it will actually make sense.
We can write.
It's better to do it this way.
Because if they.
Yeah.
It's wrong.
Yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah.
So should I just.
Okay.
So we have to have this else statement at the end.
And this else statement can actually be really useful in this situation because like I said before.
Like I said before, if just one letter is off in this mass season variable, then it's going to come
here.
So if we had some written like that, it's going to go nope, it's not equal to that, not equal to
that, not equal to that, not equal to that.
So what season is it then.
I mean your user is going to be like, I don't understand.
They might not realize they've just put a typo in here.
So we're going to make it more easy for your user to understand what's happened.
So the else is essentially a catch all.
So we could have used else maybe you might have thought well we could have used it to catch for autumn,
but it wouldn't really have been true because.
Sarah showed you if you misspelled summer, it would have said, don't forget to jump in the leaves
because that would have been the else.
Okay, so we needed to check each of them as an if and an else if.
And then finally the else becomes a catch all.
Meaning no, you didn't get any of the seasons right.
You've done something wrong.
And so it can print.
You haven't chosen a correct season.
Okay, so let's just run it as it is.
And what our program did is it came here my seasons equal to summer.
Okay.
Check the first statement.
Is it equal to summer?
Yes.
Let's print this.
And then it ignores all of this.
It doesn't even well, it doesn't run this at all.
And it just prints this statement over here.
Now, like I was explaining before, let's spell summer wrong.
So it's now checked that it's checked that that all of these and said, oh no, it's not equal to any
of these.
So finally it prints this else statement which says over here, you haven't chosen a correct season.
And obviously if we had changed this to one of the others, let's say spring, it's now going to check,
check this, check this, and then finally check this.
Oh yes, this is true print.
Remember your camera and ignore the rest.
So basically else ifs just allow you to check more than one things in a more efficient way.
So you can see there are lots of times when you would want to do something like this.
There are often occasions when you need to do more than one conditional check, and you don't put lots
of if statements because you need to make your code efficient.
You either use an if else if it's just two, otherwise use an if else if else if else if all the way
down to finally an else.
Basically, just remember that every if else statement does need an else.
And yeah, you don't forget your indenting as well.